<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>Beigesoftware, Beige-Accounting</title>
   </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Accounting of purchase, prepayments, payments tracking.">

      <h4>Sales taxes payed for raw material (producing USA).</h4>
      <p>In USA sales taxes paid for material/merchandise is "included into inventory" and they are deducting income tax.
      Term "included into inventory" means that Inventory(not exactly inventory items costs) include your all capitalized and uncapitalized business expenses (rent, goods cost, taxes, etc),
      and capitalized deducting income amount is calculated by equation,
      see <a href="acc-bobs-taxes.html">Accounting of business owner taxes, retained earnings.</a>.
      According <a href="https://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-pdf/p535.pdf">IRS 535 Business Expenses</a> sales taxes that Bob paid for materials
      are business expenses.
      IRS say that taxes (exclude Taxes assessed on the basis of income, I guess these are Bob's taxes) are Indirect Costs Required to be Capitalized.
      So Bob should set accounting settings "Extract sales taxes from purchase" to true,
      and set "is used" to true for method "PurchaseInvoice, Debit SalesTaxFromPurchase per Tax."
      Also set "is used" asset account <b>Sales Tax From Purchase</b>.
      Then fill inventory item tax category and set sales tax for each material.
      Purchase invoice will extract taxes cost into <b>Sales Tax From Purchase</b>.
      Then Bob can transfer amount from <b>Sales Tax From Purchase</b> to <b>Inventory Capitalized Cost</b>.
      </p>
      <p>Sales taxes due to buyer for your goods/service are extracted from sales revenue and they are not deducting your income tax,
      this is rule for all countries.</p>
      <p>For many other countries sales taxes (e.g. VAT) is always extracted from goods/service cost and they are deducting themselves.</p>

      <p>Here is used fake sales tax 6% for goods with cheese (only for example purpose)!</p>
      
      <p>To apply sales tax for a material/merchandise you should:
        <p>1. Add <b>Item Tax Category</b> e.g.:
          <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting merchandise sales tax category" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/item-tax-category.png" /></p>
        </p>
        <p>1. Set <b>Item Tax Category</b> for material e.g.:
          <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting set merchandise sales tax" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/set-merchandise-sales-tax.png" /></p>
        </p>
      </p>
      
      <h4>Prepayments</h4>
      <p>At 14 Jan Bob prepaid goods to Carlo's grocery:
          <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting prepayment for purchase" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/prepayment-for-purchase.png" /></p>
      </p>
      <p>It make simple accounting entries:
          <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting prepayment for purchase report" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/prepayment-for-purchase-report.png" /></p>
      </p>

      <p>
        After a document is accounted you can't change it, you can only reverse it
        and change description of its accounting entries. Beige-Accounting is designed for high load,
        this kind of software requires accuracy, otherwise you will get mess-up quickly. Just make database backup more frequently.
      </p>
      
      <h4>Purchase</h4>
      <p>
        Bob bought at Jan 15 pizza ingredients and fill purchase invoice then account it:
        <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting purchase invoice" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/purchase1.png" /></p>
        <p>Field <b>pay by date</b> is optional.</p>
        <p align="center">full report  is:</p>
        <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting purchase invoice report" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/purchase2.png" /></p>
        As you can see purchase invoice make accounting record prepayments to account payable. Only prepayment per invoice is allowed,
        otherwise you should either make prepayments and payments tracking "by hand" or divide prepayment by pieces.
      </p>

      <h4>Payments tracking</h4>
      <p>At 15 Jan Bob paid the rest to Carlo's grocery for purchase invoice#1:
          <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting payment for purchase" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/payment-for-purchase.png" /></p>
      </p>
      <p>It make simple accounting entries:
          <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting payment for purchase report" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/payment-for-purchase-report.png" /></p>
      </p>
      <p>After what purchase invoice payment tracking fields in list have changed:
          <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting payment for purchase tracking" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/purchase-payment-tracking.png" /></p>
      </p>


    </section>

  </body>

</document>
