<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>Beigesoft™ Accounting</title>
   </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Accounting of employment (payroll).">
      
      <p>Keywords: Accounting of employment (payroll).</p>
      
<p>Beige-Accounting has implemented widely used in many countries <b>tax table percentage method</b> for automatically calculation wage taxes.</p>
<p>It has implemented automatically calculation <b>wage tax = tax percent (according tables) * (gross wage - all allowances per payment)</b>. This simple method is used in USA.
In others countries it's used little more complex method <b>allowances per year</b>, which application hasn't implemented automatically yet.
</p>
<p>
  Bob has hired Rob Swallow as a cook.
  Bob uses <a href="https://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-pdf/p15.pdf">IRS Publication 15</a> (<b>IRS-ETG</b>) to accounts employment federal taxes, and
  <a href="https://www.tax.ny.gov/pdf/publications/withholding/nys50_t_nys.pdf">NYS New York State Withholding Tax</a> for state ones.
</p>
  <p>
    1. Federal Income Tax from employee wage.
    Rob has filled form W-4 and got two withholding allowances. Bob has elected percentage method, so according Table 5 (page 42 of <b>IRS-ETG</b>)
    allowance daily is 15.6 * 2 = 31.2. Bob should uses table 8 (page 45 of <b>IRS-ETG</b>) to withhold Federal Income tax,
    so he has filled Employment -  Wage tax table according it:
    <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting tax percentage method" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/wtt-federal-income.png" /></p>
  </p>
  <p>
    2. Medicare Tax from employee wage.
    According <b>IRS-ETG</b> its rate is 1.45%,
    so he has filled new Wage tax table:
    <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/wtt-meducare.png" /></p>
  </p>
  <p>
    3. Social Security Tax from employee wage.
    According <b>IRS-ETG</b> its rate is 6.2% with year wage limit 118500 USD,
    he has filled SST Wage tax table:
    <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/wtt-ss.png" /></p>
  </p>
  <p>
    4. Federal Unemployment Tax from EMPLOYER. Be sure to set its type properly (from employee or employer).
    According <b>IRS-ETG</b> its rate is 6% with year wage limit 7000 USD,
    so he has filled FUTA Wage tax table:
    <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/wtt-futa.png" /></p>
  </p>
  <p>
    5. New York Income Tax from employee wage.
    According <a href="https://www.tax.ny.gov/pdf/publications/withholding/nys50_t_nys.pdf">NYS New York State Withholding Tax</a>
    Rob's two allowances by form W-4 give him daily allowance 36.15 (Table-A on page 14). Bob uses table II-E (page 17)
    to figures NY Income tax, so he has filled NY Income Wage tax table according it:
    <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/wtt-ny-income.png" /></p>
  </p>
  <p>
    Rob has made on Jan 17 12 Pizza with bacon Frozen and 12 Pizza with cheese Frozen then has delivered them to customers.
    Bob has filled Wage document for 60 USD gross for cooking
    and 20 USD for delivering. He set tax account expense to <b>5105 Expenses</b>,
    then pressed <b>save</b>, then added wage line for cooking (account <b>Inventory direct cost temporary</b> for direct labor cost),
    and line for delivering (<b>5105 Expenses</b> for indirect labor cost):
    <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting payroll" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/wage-line-direct.png" /></p>
    <p>then pressed button <b>fill taxes</b>, then has accounted document:</p>
    <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting payroll" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/wage1.png" /></p>
    <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting payroll report" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/wage2.png" /></p>
    <p>
      As you can see cooking(direct labor) wage is accounted separately from delivery(indirect labor) one.
      For manufacturing, direct labor cost (as well as cost of materials) are usually included into cost of the final product.
      Make sure: "is it true" for your tax rules.
    </p>
  </p>
<p>
  I guess that you noticed that Bob made mistake, he forget about NY unemployment tax (<a href="https://labor.ny.gov/ui/employerinfo/quarterly-reporting.shtm">NY SUTA requirements and limit</a>
  <a href="https://labor.ny.gov/ui/bpta/contribution-rates.shtm">NY SUTA rate</a>
  <a href="https://www.tax.ny.gov/pdf/publications/withholding/nys50.pdf">NY SUTA instructions.</a>).
  So you should make sure that you made all properly according the law of your country. Just call to your tax authority and ask them.
  Otherwise if you made mistake then you will get penalty, e.g. if you deduct your income tax with wrong cost of goods sold (deducting expense is greater than you can prove).
  You have to make (and keep) records that shows these properly calculations according <a href="https://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-pdf/p583.pdf">IRS 583 Starting a business, page 12</a>.
  Beige-Accounting respect this, in addition it makes many records automatically (COGS, employment taxes, sales taxes, etc.)
  and reports to prove your business expenses.
</p>

<p>
  Trial balance after that is:
    <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting payroll balance" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/balance-payroll.png" /></p>
</p>
<h4>Allowance per year</h4>
<p>
  To use more complex method <b>allowances per year</b> don't fill allowances in tax tables. Fill allowance in wage tax line by hand.
  For example Jim Gold got 2000 EUR allowances per year for Income tax 12%. He is paid 1500 EUR per month, so tax lines will be:
  <ul>
    <li>1st month - allowance used 1500 (the rest 500) - no tax</li>
    <li>2nd month - allowance used 500 (the rest 0) - tax = (1500-500)*0.12</li>
    <li>3d, 4th ... months - allowance is 0, so tax = 1500*0.12</li>
  </ul>
</p>

    </section>

  </body>

</document>
