<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>Beigesoftware, BeigeAccounting</title>
   </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Accounting of business owner taxes, retained earnings.">
<p>
  There are three Income Tax methods used in all countries:
  <ul>
    <li>income tax = percent * (business revenues - business expenses - allowances), and usually accrued method</li>
    <li>income tax = percent * (business revenues - allowances), and usually cash method</li>
    <li>income tax = fixed amount</li>
  </ul> 
  Accrued means that business revenue/expense is occurred when you bought or sold something (goods, services, rent etc) even unpaid.
  Cash - when you earn money or paid ones, but not prepayments, i.e. for already sold/purchase goods/service.
  According <a href="https://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-pdf/p583.pdf">IRS 583 Starting a business</a> page 6
  Bob as sole proprietor should pay Income Tax, Self-employment tax. He should pay estimated income tax
  by April 18 (see Form 1040-ES). For manufacturing (according <a href="https://www.irs.gov/businesses/small-businesses-self-employed/capitalization-period-of-direct-and-indirect-costs">IRS Capitalization Period of Direct and Indirect Costs</a>)
  direct business expenses such as cost of goods sold is made automatically
  directly on gross income (business) expense account <b>Cost Of Goods Sold (COGS)</b>. All other expenses is accounted on asset account
  <b>Inventory capitalized cost (ICC)</b>. To calculate amount of <b>Inventory capitalized cost</b> to be expense
  use equation and trial balance at the start and the end of the year:
  <pre style="white-space: pre-wrap;">
    1. Simplified Production Absorption Ratio = (ICC end - ICC start) / (Inventory end - Inventory start + COGS end)
    2. ICC amount to be expense = (ICC end - ICC start) - Inventory end * Simplified Production Absorption Ratio
  </pre>
  At the start Bob's balance is zero. For example at the end of the year Inventory = 1500USD, COGS = 240000USD,
  ICC = 25000USD. So Bob will make accounting entries Debit COGS Additional Credit ICC
  for 25000 - 1500 * 25000 /(1500 + 240000) = 24844.72USD
  <p>Of cause Bob should makes several accounting entries for each type of expense (rent, payroll tax1, etc) by using Simplified Production Absorption Ratio calculated from whole accounts.</p>
</p>
  
  <h4>Bob's earnings.</h4>
  <p>After Bob made all business revenues and expenses his gross income is:
    <pre style="white-space:pre-wrap">
      gross income = sum(gross income revenue accounts) - sum(gross income expense accounts)
    </pre>
    His Self-employment tax is also none-capitalized cost and gross income expense.
    <p>
      The final closing accounting entries are:
      <ul>
        <li>for each gross income revenue account for its end amount: Debit [gross income revenue account] Credit Bob's earnings.</li>
        <li>for each gross income expense account for its end amount: Debit Bob's earnings Credit [gross income expense account].</li>
        <li>Extract income tax from gross income: Debit Bob's earnings Credit Taxes Payable Federal Income Tax for tax amount.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </p>
  
    </section>

  </body>

</document>
