<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>Beigesoft™ Accounting</title>
   </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Mark to Market (financial) accounting, import data from tax accounting.">
      <p>Keywords: Mark To Market accounting Vs. Tax accounting, current market value, fair value, import data from tax accounting, accounting of business (trade) name.</p>
      <h4>Mark to Market(financial) accounting.</h4>
      <p>
        The law (IRS) demands Bob to keeps entries (in either single entry or in double entries accounting system)
        to estimates his taxes in calendar year period. Bob wants to estimates his real business results
        monthly. Market accounting (double entries system) based on rule:
<pre style="white-space: pre-wrap;">
Assets - Liabilities = current market value of Bob's business (How much he can earn if he sell it right now) = Owner's equity
</pre>
      </p>
      <p>
        The most entries from Tax accounting is relevant to Market one. Excluding entries are:
        <ul>
          <li>Property deprecation</li>
          <li>Closing entries (yearly)</li>
          <li>All bad debts entries</li>
        </ul>
      </p>

      <p>Bob unpacked files from <b>beigesoft-accountingoio-ajetty-bin.zip</b> into new folder <b>accounting-market</b>,
        then he copied keystore form <b>accounting-tax</b>:
      <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/market-acc-ks.png" /></p>
      </p>
      <p>
        Then (before starting and creating new database) he edited XML file <b>\WEB-INF\web.xml</b> to change new database ID into 2:
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/market-acc-id.png" /></p>
      </p>
      <p>Bob started using Beige Accounting Market in the same way as described in <a href="acc-settings.html">Software installation, accounting settings, chart of accounts, started capital.</a>,
        except "Chart of accounts", "Expenses" and "Started capital".
      </p>

      <h4>Import data from tax accounting.</h4>
      <p>To use WEB-services on intranet (localhost) Bob installed Bouncy Castle Crypto Provider and A-Jetty CA certificate as described in <a href="import-db-web.html">Import database with WEB-service.</a></p>
      <p>
        He launched source database Tax Beige Accounting on port 8444.
        Then he launched market accounting on port 8443, new market database will be created with ID=2.
      </p>
      <p>
        He uses "menu - about" to know database ID:
      </p>
      <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/tax-acc-about.png" /></p>
      <p>
        He added Replication accounting method with entries filters:
      </p>
      <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/replication-acc-method.png" /></p>
      <p>
        He filled import acc. entries form (WEB-service address is "https://localhost:8444/bsa8444/secure/sendEntities", then fill user and password (that matched to Tax database) and pressed replicate:
      </p>
      <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting import from tax to market(business) accounting" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/import_acc_entries_form.png" /></p>
      <p>
        Report of import acc. entries is:
      </p>
      <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/import_acc_entries_result.png" /></p>
      
      <h4>Property asset market cost</h4>
      <p>If you bought something (not for resale), then you can't sold it for the same price. Bob thinks that he can sold his Ford
      right now (in January) for 20000 USD, so he reports Ford value loss:</p>
      <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/ford_cost_loss.png" />
      </p>
      <p>* this loss not exceed ford deprecation at the end of the year, so it's taxable (business) expense.</p>

      <h4>Accounting of bad debts</h4>
      <p>In opposite to tax accounting rules, Bob wants to report loss immediately. Funny coffee shop bad debt is 67.47 - 33.73 = 33.74.
         If IRS has approved this bad debt, then Bob's income tax deducting will be roughly 33.74 * 25% = 8.44 (25 is predicted tax rate).
         So he created new asset account <b>Income Tax Deducting</b>:
      </p>
      <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/income-tax-deducting-acc.png" /></p>
      <p>* ID for account must be a word without spaces maximum 25 letters!</p>
      <p>Then Bob transferred 64.47 and 33.73 into it (with same way as bad debt in tax accounting), then transferred 25.30 from it into <b>Other losses</b>:</p>
      <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/acc-market-bad-debt.png" /></p>

      <p>* to be brief sample database <b>bobs-pizza-market.sqlite</b> contains of summary revenue and expenses entries instead of lot of Purchase and Sales invoices,
      so trial balance on 31 Jan is:</p>
      <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/market-trial-jan.png" /></p>
      <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/market-trial-jan-1.png" /></p>
      
      <h4>Closing entries monthly, balance sheet.</h4>
      <p>Bob made on 31 Jan closing entries into <b>Retained Earnings</b> account:
      </p>
      <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting closing entries" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/market-closing-jan.png" /></p>
      <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting closing entries" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/market-closing-jan-1.png" /></p>
      
      <p>After that gross revenue is 9,032.9287. Bob's income tax roughly is 9,032.9287 * 25% = 2258.2322, so Bob transferred
      it from <b>Retained Earnings</b>:</p>
      <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/market-jan-inc-tax.png" /></p>
      
      <p>As a result the balance sheet on 31 Jan is:</p>
      <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/market-jan-balance.png" /></p>
      <p>So Bob earn 6,774.70USD in January(*) and his business market value is 46,774.70USD.</p>
      <p>* take note that it is a simple example which does not included other taxes and their properly rates, also liabilities such taxes must be payed.</p>
      
      <h4>Accounting of business (trade) name.</h4>
      <p>In February Bob has sold pizza for 37,000 USD, expenses is 11,000 USD. So gross income = 26,000 USD,
      income tax = 6,500 USD (Bob earned 19,500 in Feb vs 6,774 in Jan). Bob closed February with result: his business market cost is 66,274.70.
      But at this time (on Feb 29 evening) a reliable businessman called Bob and asked him that he wants to buy Bob's pizza business for 80,000 USD.
      Bob refused this offer and reported this event (increased business value for 13,725.30) with new asset account <b>Bob's pizza name</b>:
      </p>
      <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting of business (trade) name" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/market-business-name.png" /></p>
      <p>Business (trade) name value always reflects to number of customers that prefer its (business maker's) goods or services.</p>
      <p>So February balance sheet is:</p>
      <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting balance sheet" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/market-feb-balance-sheet.png" /></p>
      <p>* Despite of rough income tax estimation, it would be better to use separate expense accounts for "expenses that deduct income tax" and "that don't".</p>
    </section>

  </body>

</document>
