<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>Beigesoftware, Beige-Accounting</title>
   </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Accounting of manufacturing (producing).">

      <b>Beige-Accounting automatically calculates cost of product = cost of materials
       plus additional costs (direct labor, packaging etc), this method is widely used in many countries.</b>
      <p>
        The main document for accounting of manufacturing expenses is <a href="https://www.irs.gov/businesses/small-businesses-self-employed/capitalization-period-of-direct-and-indirect-costs">IRS Capitalization Period of Direct and Indirect Costs</a>.
        At Jan 17 Rob made 12 Pizza with bacon frozen and 12 Pizza with cheese frozen. Where are two documents for manufacturing:
        <ul>
          <li>Manufacturing process that makes a <b>product in progress</b> by using materials and usually direct labor cost, and makes accounting, draw material and warehouse entries</li>
          <li>Manufacture. It just transfer completed <b>product in progress</b> into <b>finished product</b>, and makes accounting, draw material and warehouse entries</li>
        </ul>
        Bob fill manufacturing process for 12 Pizza with cheese frozen:
        <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting manufacturing" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/manufacture-process1.png" /></p>
        <p>Field <b>Site from</b> in use material line is optional. If it's empty then withdrawal will be from the first warehouse
        site/s with available item/s.</p>
        <p>Bob added one half of direct labor cost 45.91 (22.955) from Inventory capitalized cost temporary according Wage full report.
        After completing and accounting full report is:</p>
        <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting manufacturing report" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/manufacture-process2.png" /></p>
        <p>
          Then Bob fill and account Manufacture based on Manufacturing process above:
          <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/manufacture1.png" /></p>
          <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/manufacture2.png" /></p>
        </p>
        <p>
          Bob make same documents for 12 Pizza with bacon frozen.
        </p>
      </p>

    </section>

  </body>

</document>
