<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>Beigesoft™, Beige-Accounting</title>
   </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Multi-currency. Exchange gain or loss. Exchange difference.">
      
      <p>Keywords: multi-currency, exchange gain or loss, exchange difference, foreign currency transactions.</p>

      <p>* New features described in this article available in version 1.1.7 (in source code right now). In current published version 1.1.6 you can only report exchange gain or loss, you can't print sales invoice in foreign currency and you can't track payments in foreign currency.
      </p>
      
      <h4>Multi-currency, exchange gain or loss.</h4>
      <p>If you sell a merchandise that is paid in foreign currency, and you use the ACCRUAL method (you have to report revenue for unpaid sales),
        and currency exchange rate is different when the payment occurred, then you face "exchange difference".
        You will never face an exchange difference if you use the CASH method, except if you sell currency.
        In that case, it's not actually "exchange difference", it's ordinal "difference between purchase price and sales one", i.e. currency is ordinal goods in that case.</p>
      <p>The most countries have a similar law about foreign currency transactions, that is:
      <ul>
        <li>you have to make records in national currency (and language).</li>
        <li>selling/buying transaction is made with the current exchange rate (booking date)</li>
        <li>payment transaction is made with the current exchange rate (payment date)</li>
        <li>difference between booking and payment rates (gain or loss) is business revenue or expense.</li>
      </ul>
      </p>
      <h4>Selling goods that paid with foreign currency example</h4>
      <p>
        Create new invoice and set foreign currency to EURO and exchange rate is 1.12 (on 16 Jul 2016), add 2 "Pizza with cheese frozen" for 14.11 EURO:
        <p align="center"><img alt="multi currency invoice example" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/salesmc1.png" /></p>
      </p>
      <p>
        Add 100 pounds of "bacon" for 10.15 EURO:
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/salesmc2.png" /></p>
      </p>
      <p>
        After adding 28.5 miles of "delivering to the seaport" for 4.93 EURO and accounting full report is:
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/salesmc3.png" /></p>
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/salesmc3-1.png" /></p>
        <p>* as you can see, accounting entries are made in national currency.</p>
      </p>
      <p>See <a href="acc-overseas-sales.html">Overseas sales. Advanced internationalization.</a> to make invoice translated in foreign language (if it's need).</p>
      <p>
        Final invoice report for foreign customer is:
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/salesmc4.png" /></p>
      </p>
      <p>Payment is made on 26 Jul 2016, and exchange rate is 1.14, so you have to report additional revenue "exchange gain" (1,349.45 - 1,325.78 = 23.67):
<pre style="white-space: pre-wrap;">
27 Jun 2016 10:26AM, Debit CashInBank."#1236786817 in Bank" Credit AccReceivable."OOO Berezka" for 1,349.45 USD
* after that the balance AccReceivable."OOO Berezka" is -23.67 (negative)

27 Jun 2016 11:15AM, Debit AccReceivable."OOO Berezka" Credit ExchangeGain for 23.67 USD
</pre>
        * of course, you have to report additional business expenses like "fee for wire transfer", "fee for currency exchange", etc.
      </p>
      <p>You should add new account "Exchange Gain" of type "Income revenue":
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/salesmc5.png" /></p>
      </p>
      <p>
        Accounting entries above made with documents:
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/salesmc6.png" /></p>
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/salesmc7.png" /></p>
      </p>
      <p>
        You have to fill in "Payment From" field "Total FO" (total in foreign currency) for payments tracking (in foreign currency for such invoices):
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/salesmc8.png" /></p>
      </p>
    </section>

  </body>

</document>
