<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>Beigesoftware, Beige-Accounting</title>
   </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Accounting of purchase, prepayments, payments tracking.">

      <p>Keywords: Accounting of purchase, prepayments, sales taxes from purchase, payments tracking, bank reconciliation.</p>

      <h4>Sales taxes payed for raw material (producing USA).</h4>
      <p>According <a href="https://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-pdf/p535.pdf">IRS 535 Business Expenses, Page 18</a> sales taxes that Bob paid for materials
      are business expenses (sales taxes are included into material cost),  i.e. they are deducting income tax:
<pre style="white-space: pre-wrap;">
...
Any sales tax you pay on a service for your business, or on the purchase or use of property
in your business is treated as part of the cost of the service or property.
If the service or the cost or use of the property is a deductible business expense,
you can deduct the tax as part of that service or cost.
If the property is merchandise bought for resale, the sales tax is part of the cost of the merchandise.
...
  * I think here term "property" also means materials and supplies (as well as merchandise), any way for any seller these all means "goods/merchandise".
  * term "deduct an expense" means that you can deduct its cost (part or whole) from gross income, so as a result the tax is decreased.
  deducting in double entry system usually makes with:
  Credit [An Asset Account] Debit [An Temporary Gross Income Expense Account] for deducting amount
  at the end of accounting period all temporary gross income expenses/revenues accounts are closed on gross income account (or directly on retaining earnings/loses)
</pre>  
        That is sales taxes from purchase is included into inventory and they become expenses automatically as part of Cost Of Goods Sold (method FIFO in this case).
        So Bob should set accounting settings "Extract sales taxes from purchase" to No,
        and set "is used" to No for method "PurchaseInvoice, Debit SalesTaxFromPurchase per Tax.":
          <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting settings - sales taxes from purchase" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/settings-sales-tax-from-purchase.png" /></p>
        Also he should set "is used" to No asset account <b>Sales Tax From Purchase</b>.
        Then he should fill inventory item tax category and set sales tax for each material.
        Purchase invoice will extracts taxes cost into <b>Sales Tax From Purchase</b> account.
      </p>
      <p>
        If you have to use different method to account sales tax from purchase,
        then set accounting settings "Extract sales taxes from purchase" to Yes,
        and set "is used" to Yes for method "PurchaseInvoice, Debit SalesTaxFromPurchase per Tax."
        Also you should set "is used" to true asset account <b>Sales Tax From Purchase</b>.
        This is required in case of using "inventory capitalized costs" method (for USA example <a href="https://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-pdf/p538.pdf">IRS 538, Page 18 Uniform Capitalization Rules</a>).
        Capitalized cost became expense partially depends of ending inventory (product).
      </p>
      <p>For many other countries sales taxes (e.g. VAT) from purchases is always extracted from goods/service cost and they are deducting themselves (taxes from sales, not deducting income tax).</p>
      <p>Sales taxes imposed on the buyer from your sales of your goods/service are extracted from sales revenue, and you have to pay them, this rule is applied in all countries.</p>

      <p>Here is used fake sales tax 6% for goods with cheese (only for example purpose)!</p>
      
      <p>To apply sales tax for a material/merchandise/service you should:
        <p>1. Add <b>Item Tax Category</b> e.g.:
          <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting merchandise sales tax category" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/item-tax-category.png" /></p>
        </p>
        <p>1. Set <b>Item Tax Category</b> for material e.g.:
          <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting set merchandise sales tax" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/set-merchandise-sales-tax.png" /></p>
        </p>
      </p>
      
      <h4>Prepayments</h4>
      <p>Bob has prepaid goods to Carlo's grocery on 14 Jan:
          <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting prepayment for purchase" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/prepayment-for-purchase.png" /></p>
      </p>
      <p>"Prepayment for purchase" has made simple accounting entries:
          <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting prepayment for purchase report" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/prepayment-for-purchase-report.png" /></p>
      </p>

      <p>
        After a document is accounted you can't change it, you can only reverse it
        and can change description of its accounting entries. Beige-Accounting is designed for high load job,
        this kind of software requires accuracy, otherwise you will get mess-up quickly. Just make database backup more frequently.
      </p>
      
      <h4>Purchase</h4>
      <p>
        Bob has bought pizza ingredients on Jan 15 then has filled purchase invoice then has accounted it:
        <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting purchase invoice" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/purchase1.png" /></p>
        <p>Field <b>pay by date</b> is optional.</p>
        <p align="center">full report  is:</p>
        <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting purchase invoice report" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/purchase2.png" /></p>
        <p>* As you can see purchase invoice automatically makes accounting record prepayments to account payable. Only prepayment per invoice is allowed (has implemented),
        otherwise you should make prepayments and payments tracking "by hand".</p>
        <p>* You also can see that sales tax for cheese is included into its cost, i.e. it is not extracted.</p>
      </p>

      <h4>Payments tracking</h4>
      <p>Bob has paid the rest to Carlo's grocery for purchase invoice#1 on 15 Jan:
          <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting payment for purchase" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/payment-for-purchase.png" /></p>
      </p>
      <p>Document "Payment for purchase" has made simple accounting entries:
          <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting payment for purchase report" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/payment-for-purchase-report.png" /></p>
      </p>
      <p>Purchase invoice's payment's tracking fields in the list are changed after that:
          <p align="center"><img alt="Beige-Accounting payment for purchase tracking" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/purchase-payment-tracking.png" /></p>
      </p>

      <h4>Bank reconciliation</h4>
      <p>When bank account balance in your accounting system (software or book) is not same as in the bank (in the bank statement),
        then you have to make adjusting entries. This is called "bank reconciliation".
        For example yesterday you had received check for 500USD from customer "Firm A" and made accounting entry:
        <pre>
Debit CashInBank.Account#243443354 for 500USD Credit AccountsReceivable.FirmA for 500USD
        </pre>
        After that your bank account balance is 10000USD (in your accounting system).
        Today you have received the bank statement that is saying that the check was rejected and you was charged for 10USD additionally cause that "wrong check"
        and the balance is 9490USD.
        So you have to make two adjusting entries:
        <pre>
Credit CashInBank.Account#243443354 for 500USD Debit AccountsReceivable.FirmA for 500USD
Credit CashInBank.Account#243443354 for 10USD Debit Expenses.BankExpenses for 10USD
        </pre>
      </p>

    </section>

  </body>

</document>
