<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>Beigesoft™ Accounting</title>
   </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="How to protect your data.">
  
    <p>Keywords: encryption, data protection.</p>

    <h4>Why you should learn about data protection.</h4>
    <p>If you a business owner and a data about your customers was leaked, then you will get problems. And so does if you are a freelance accountant.
      Learn about data protection is not difficult.
    </p>
    
    <h4>The facts.</h4>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          It was about 19 years ago, when a computer with an operation system catches a virus just after connection to Internet. That is user did not open WEB-browser. 
        </li>
        <li>
          It was about 8 years ago, when a web-browser allowed a scam-script to rewrite master boot record (the heart of file system) in hard drive. That virus was trying to force victims to pay many.
        </li>
        <li>
          You never need a lat of features in your software that scams uses for cheating you.
        </li>
        <li>
          Your software might already affected by scam-ware, and you might never know about it, but scam knows anything from your computer.
        </li>
      </ul>
      * Here word "scam" means a person who deprives any your value (tangible/intangible) by using non-robbery's methods like cheating.
    </p>

    <h4>That they do the best for you (to protect your data)</h4>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>They removed, restricted scam-friendly features, the leader (it seams only) is Android, an Android application can't read files belongs to another applications, and you set by yourself permissions to the shared storage.</li>
        <li>They track activity of your account (all social networks do it). So if scam stole your password and trying to sign-in under your account from another device, then you will be informed about it (they even can block your account without your request).</li>
        <li>They allow to use your social network account for authorization in other sites. Using "master" account to login to another sites is preferred authorization method, cause they track your activity.</li>
        <li>They force you to install software from well known sources like "a software store".</li>
        <li>Of course, things like encryption, free anti-scam-ware.</li>
      </ul>
      * Here "They" means IT specialists - programmers...
    </p>
    
    <h4>That they do the worst for you</h4>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>Despite of too long "VERY bad practice" they force you to use scam-friendly features. The leader is Linux desktop Gnome 3. They remove useful feature standard system tray, added new one, to enable useful features they forced you to install additional software and PLUGIN!!! for firefox that has permissions to your file system.</li>
        <li>They force you to install and use unsigned software from "untrusted sources" to resolve your problems.</li>
        <li>Offer recovering software in non write-protected places like HDD or flash, cause very complex scamware can poisons them and breaks their protection.</li>
        <li>Do not track usage of their digital signature.</li>
      </ul>
      "untrusted sources" means any non well known Internet sites.
    </p>

    <h4>That they must do for you</h4>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>A web-browser can upload and download a file (files/folder) interactively. Browser's plugins and page's scripts must delegate to the browser "upload/download" file interactively only. They must has permissions to only their "sandbox" file-system.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <h4>That you do the worst for you</h4>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>Install unneeded software (especially from untrusted sources).</li>
        <li>Use weak passwords</li>
        <li>Do not learn about data protection</li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <h4>Strong password</h4>
    <p>
      The weakest passwords are:
      <ul>
        <li>Of course, qwerty like passwords - "admin", "1234567"...</li>
        <li>Generated passwords e.g. "87ghgjs6KYfgluy" - user can't remember such password and force to stick note with this password to its monitor.</li>
      </ul>
      The strong passwords are ease to remember. These are set of words e.g. "raccooneatstone165".
    </p>
    <p>
      Anyway, strong passwords vulnerable to scam-cameras (hidden cameras). So using browser's password storage is preferred way.
      But this storage must be under your master account (to track activity). It's also desirable that browser doesn't store passwords locally, only cashes them from account Internet storage.
      You should sign out when you leave your computer for a long time (e.g. a vocation).
    </p>
    
    <h4>How to protect you from scams completely.</h4>
    <p>
      There is way to  protect you from scams completely. It's all about encryption, digital signature, global tracking of using digital signature, save storing key for digital signature.
    </p>
    <p>
      What is encryption? It's encoding message (text, file...) with an encryption algorithm and a key. Encrypted message is not readable.
    </p>
    <p>
      Symmetric encryption algorithms use symmetric secret key for encryption and decryption.
    </p>
    <p>
      Asymmetric encryption algorithms use asymmetric secret (private) key for encryption and asymmetric public key for decryption.
      Asymmetric algorithms also allow to encrypt information with asymmetric public key and decrypt it with asymmetric secret (private) key.
      In these both cases key used for encryption can not be used for decryption.
    </p>
    <p>
      Digital signature is information encrypted with asymmetric secret (private) key.
      Public key is available for all, so anyone can use it to decrypt signature,
      and this successful decryption means that signature is checked.
    </p>
    <p>A scam can try to match a private key by using the public one and the signature. But it's takes very long time even for high-performance computers.
      So common way is stole private key, or stole keystore and match its pass-phrase.
    </p>
    <p>
      It must be a "device to sign" and "global tracking of signature usage" to resolve these problems. "Device to sign" makes signature itself.
      There is no way to get private key from it. It contains of your private key to make your signature and contains of its own private key to report using your signature to global server.
      The best way is using this device as your only digital passport, so it also will contain your photo and other information.
      Of course this requires changing law and adapting software, but finally you will be totally protected from scams.
      You will use this device for any operation - open a door (home, car, hotel room), sing in to computer or any site, bank transfer, ATM withdrawal, etc.
      You even will no need to use pin for making signature. A cashier will check photo from your device.
    </p>
    
    </section>

  </body>

</document>
