<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>Beigesoft™ Accounting Privacy Policy</title>
   </properties>

  <body>

  <section name="Beigesoft™ Accounting Privacy Policy">

<h4 align="center">Beigesoft™ Accounting Privacy Policy.</h4>
<h5 align="center">All Beigesoft™ Accounting versions.</h5>
<p>  
  Beigesoft™ Accounting collects (stores) your data only inside database file.
</p>
<p>
  If you set option <b>Show debug messages</b> to <b>ON</b> and <b>Debug detail level</b> to equals or grater than <b>30000</b>
  then log files <b>beige-accounting0.log</b> and <b>beige-accounting1.log</b> will contain sensitive data.
  In that case, if you are going to send these log files to a programmer (who customize this application)
  then you must remove sensitive data from these files.
</p>
<p>
  This is WEB-application, so you have to use the newest version of WEB-browser. You should avoid to install any WEB-browser plugins.
</p>

<h5 align="center">Beigesoft™ Accounting standalone versions.</h5>
<p>These versions are based on embedded private A-Jetty WEB-server.
  This private WEB-server is not available from outside your computer (or Android device).
  These versions require authorization with strong password (created by you).
  They allow maximum 6 fail login attempts. Session will be blocked in 15 minutes after 6-th fail login attempts. You should periodically check file <b>secure.log</b> that contains authorization information.
  These versions use modern encryption algorithms with strong keys for HTTPS connection and for safe encrypted file exchanging.
  These are multi-database versions, you can create new and switch database from WEB-interface.
  If you a going to sent database file to another computer then you have to use WEB-interface for encrypting this file.
</p>

<h5 align="center">Beigesoft™ Accounting on embedded A-Jetty for standard computer.</h5>
<p>
  Your data is in database file, default is <b>webapp/beigeaccounting.sqlite</b>.
  You are able to copy (backup) database to a private place by using standard file manager.
  Keystore with secret keys for encryption is in <b>ks</b> folder. It is protected with strong password (created by you).
  You should set strong password for your OS account. It's advisable to set startup BIOS password on your computer. 
</p>

<h5 align="center">Beigesoft™ Accounting on embedded A-Jetty for Android.</h5>
<p>
  Your data (SQLite databases), beige-accounting.log, secure.log, keystore (with secret keys) are in private application storage.
  There is no way to read these files from there. Only this application can read and write these files.
  You can lost your data if you forget password (for keystore or/and application),
  so you should backup database files by using WEB-interface.
  This requires Beige-Accounting standalone version on another computer (or Android device),
  cause application encrypts files with public key from another Beige-Accounting.
  Only another Beige-Accounting (whose public key used for encryption) can decrypts these encrypted files.
  Avoid to print PDF file if Google Chrome download them into shared storage (download folder), cause any other application
  that has permissions to this storage can read your PDF file. At least avoid to install any additional applications that requires permission to the storage,
  already installed PDF viewer will do. If you connect your Android device to a computer in MTP mode, then these PDF files will be also accessible to all computer's software.
</p>

<h5 align="center">Beigesoft™ Accounting cloud version.</h5>
<p>
  Cloud (Internet available) version is more difficult to keep your data private, so use it only when it's necessary.
  You must yourself handle strong passwords and reliable HTTPS connection.
</p>

<p align="center"><a href="privacypolicy-ru.html">Беижсофт™ Бухгалтерия. Политика конфиденциальности.</a></p>
<p align="center"><a href="https://sites.google.com/site/beigesoftware/privacypolicy">Beigesoft™ Accounting Privacy Policy.</a></p>


    </section>

  </body>

</document>
