<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>Beigesoft™ Accounting. Export/import data to/from CSV file.</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <!-- The body of the document contains a number of sections -->
    <section name="Beigesoft™ Accounting. Export/import data to/from CSV file.">

      <h4>CSV format</h4>
      <p>
        Data separators:
        <ul>
          <li>comma</li>
          <li>semicolon</li>
          <li>etc</li>
        </ul>
        line ending:
        <ul>
          <li>CR/LF - Windows</li>
          <li>LF - Linux</li>
          <li>CR - Mac</li>
        </ul>
        Date formats:
        <ul>
          <li>MM/dd/yyyy - USA</li>
          <li>dd/MM/yyyy - others</li>
          <li>etc</li>
        </ul>
        Text encoding:
        <ul>
          <li>UTF-8</li>
          <li>US-ASCII</li>
          <li>ISO-8859-1</li>
          <li>etc</li>
        </ul>
        Columns names may be present or not.
      </p>
      
      <h4>Common CSV data models and services</h4>
      <p> Model org.beigesoft.model.ECsvColumnType:
        <ul>
          <li>STRING</li>
          <li>BOOLEAN</li>
          <li>INTEGER</li>
          <li>NUMERIC</li>
          <li>DATE</li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>
        Persistable model org.beigesoft.persistable.CsvMethod
        <ul>
          <li>AHasIdLongNameVersion fields</li>
          <li>charsetName, String, not null, Charset encoding name, "UTF-8" default.</li>
          <li>columnSep, String[5], not null, Column separator, comma default.</li>
          <li>hasHeader, Boolean, not null, if the first row contains of columns names, false default.</li>
          <li>columns - List(CsvColumn), Csv Columns all or useful to read</li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>
        Persistable model org.beigesoft.persistable.CsvColumn
        <ul>
          <li>AHasIdLongNameVersion fields</li>
          <li>itsOwner - CsvMethod</li>
          <li>itsType, ECsvColumnType, not null</li>
          <li>itsIndex, Integer, not null, start from 1 index.</li>
          <li>sourceIndex, Integer, not null, start from 1 index in source file cause some columns might be omitted.</li>
          <li>textDelimiter - String, null default, Column's text braced with delimiters, null default,
            e.g. quoted - "taxes, penalty and other fees are included"</li>
          <li>dataFormat - String, null default, Column's data format, null default, e.g. "dd/MM/yyyy" for Date,
            "space,comma" for number "123 31,78EUR", "true,false" for Boolean</li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>Basic reading service that reads next line from CSV file ICsvReader, methods:
        <ul>
          <li>readNextRow(Map&lt;String, Object&gt; pReqVars, pReader Reader, CsvMethod pCsvMethod) - returns List&lt;String&gt; list of String values of all columns from next row, null if no more rows left. May throws an Exception</li>
        </ul>
        This is performance, memory and algorithmically friendly service.
      </p>

      <h4>Import bank statement. Semi-automatically bank reconciliation.</h4>
      <p>
        When CSV file contains of entry like:
<pre style="white-space: pre-wrap;">
  01/01/2018,check#123 wrong signature,VOIDED,123.45
</pre>
then it means that check#123 for 123.45 was canceled, so application should try to find payment or prepayment with matching amount and date and suggest to reverse that document. 
      </p>
      <p>Business logic "completing bank statement line":
      <ul>
        <li>when field "resultAction" is empty, then field is not yet completed</li>
        <li>where is two complete actions - "adding new record" and "report already matching record"</li>
        <li><b>when "finding canceled mode" is set to on and line marked as "canceled"</b> - matching non-reversed and reversed accounting prepayments/payments/accounting entries will be listed - action "reverse" will be appeared for non-reversed records and action "report matching" will be appeared for already reversed records.</li>
        <li>when line has status "ACCEPTED", then matching non-reversed prepayments/payments/accounting entries will be listed to report "matching", actions "new payment/prepayment/accounting entry" will be appeared in any case</li>
      </ul>
      </p>
      <p>
        After user made any suggesting action, result should be listed for the line where action was made, e.g. "created reversing payment#67 for 12.34USD".
      </p>
      <p>Persistable model BankCsvMethod:
        <ul>
          <li>AHasIdLongNameVersion fields</li>
          <li>csvMethod, CsvMethod, not null</li>
          <li>dateCol - CsvColumn, not null, date</li>
          <li>amountCol - CsvColumn, not null, amount, Standard value is dot separated
            number without group separators e.g. "11245.23", otherwise accepted
            formats: "COMMA,SPACE" European standard - "11 245,45",
            but in that case column value must be braced with text delimiter,
            e.g. quotes; "COMMA,NONE" - "11245,45". All other separators should be
            original, i.e. dot is ".", e.g. ".,NONE" is default format</li>
          <li>descriptionCol - CsvColumn, if used, description</li>
          <li>statusCol - CsvColumn, if used, column that contains of CANCELED or NOT information</li>
          <li>acceptedWords - String, if used, comma separated words that mean that entry was ACCEPTED, e.g. "OK,ACCEPTED" or single value "true"</li>
          <li>voidedWords - String, if used, comma separated words that mean that entry was CANCELED, e.g. "VOIDED,CANCELED" or single value "false"</li>
        </ul>
        "finding canceled mode" is set to on when statusCol and voidedWords are filled.
      </p>
      <p>Persistable model BankStatement:
        <ul>
          <li>APersistableBaseVersion fields, version changed time</li>
          <li>bankAccount, BankAccount, not null</li>
          <li>itsDate - Date, not null</li>
          <li>sourceName - String, CSV file name + BankCsvMethod name</li>
          <li>itsLines - List&lt;BankStatementLine&gt;</li>
          <li>description - String, description created by user, e.g. "line #45 made mistake, see adjusting entry #123"</li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>Persistable model BankStatementLine, constTypeCode() = 1010:
        <ul>
          <li>APersistableBaseVersion fields, implements IHasTypeCode, version changed time</li>
          <li>itsOwner, BankStatement, not null, read only field</li>
          <li>itsDate - Date, not null, from CSV, read only field</li>
          <li>itsAmount - BigDecimal, not null, negative or positive - from CSV, read only field</li>
          <li>descriptionStatus - String, from CSV if present, read only field, if statusCol presents, then string value will be present here.</li>
          <li>itsStatus - EBankEntryStatus.ACCEPTED/VOIDED, ACCEPTED default or from CSV according settings, read only field</li>
          <li>resultAction - EBankEntryAction.CREATE/MATCH, null default, read only, create record or found matching record</li>
          <li>resultDescription, String, if line completed, read only field, e.g. "created PaymentTo#12665" or "found PaymentTo#12665"</li>
          <li>resultRecordId, Long, if new record made, read only field</li>
          <li>resultRecordType, EBankEntryResultType.ACC_ENTRY/PAYMENTFROM/PREPAYMENTFROM/PAYMENTTO/PREPAYMENTTO, if new record made, read only field</li>
        </ul>
        Only action per line is allowed. If user made mistake, then it should fix it "by hand", i.e. add adjusting accounting entry, etc.
      </p>

      <h4>Export goods/services list to POS</h4>
      <p>In theory, CSV price list should contains:
        <ul>
          <li><b>required data:</b></li>
          <li>goods/service name</li>
          <li>goods/service ID (code)</li>
          <li>price (of course)</li>
          <li>tax method - describes which taxes applies and how, is it included into price</li>
          <li><b>optional data:</b></li>
          <li>is it service</li>
          <li>unit of measure</li>
          <li>its category name and ID, e.g. "chocolate bars"/201</li>
          <li>price method - describes discount, etc. e.g. 15% off at the mornings...</li>
          <li>barcode</li>
          <li>picture file name</li>
          <li>available quantity - to prevent selling more than given number, it may be 0 to stop selling this goods.</li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>In real life POS wants other data, but most of them are usually optional:
        <ul>
          <li>is available</li>
          <li>cost</li>
          <li>supplier</li>
          <li>location</li>
          <li>etc</li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>
        There are also numerous means to pass tax and price methods:
        <li>
          <li>several fields - tax rate, is included in price, etc</li>
          <li>several fields - tax name, tax rate</li>
          <li>several fields - tax name1, tax rate1, tax name2, tax rate2, etc</li>
          <li>only field - aggregate tax rate</li>
          <li>several fields - etc</li>
          <li>only field - discount</li>
          <li>only field - ID of tax method</li>
          <li>only field - ID of price method</li>
        </li>
      </p>
      <p>Tax method - on item or on invoice basis is settled in POS for all goods.</p>
      <p>Shop in downtown use different prices than shop in suburb. In other hand online and retail prices usually different.
        Beigesoft Webstore (it's actually trading system) has persistable models:
        <ul>
          <li>PriceCategoryOfItems - name (e.g. retail shop#1), description</li>
          <li>PriceCategoryOfBuyers - name, description</li>
          <li>PriceCategory - name (e.g. retail shop#1), item price category (required), buyer price category (optional), is retail only (to prevent use it in online WEB-Store)</li>
          <li>PriceGoods - goods, price category (e.g. retail shop#1), price</li>
        </ul>
      </p>

    </section>

  </body>

</document>
